Do you have to be fake to be polite?

While I was studying abroad in France, my friend Cati had a nice explanation for why French people seemed rude sometimes. What was rude to us seemed honest to them, and what was polite to us seemed fake to them. 

Of course, this is a generalization that plays out across personality types just as often as cultures. But I saw it happen after buying a bus ticket from Brussels to Paris. 

I ordered an Uber to the bus station probably ten minutes too late, and even with the Uber driver making Jason Bourne moves[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2ETruidd5lQ], it looked like we wouldn't make it on time. He cut me off when I started complaining about having already bought the ticket: "It's not like it's a flight or anything -- there's no need to exaggerate."

My Uber driver was right, but it seemed a bit rude to me. He wasn't French (he was a Moroccan guy living in Belgium named Akif), but it was exactly what Cati had described.

Americans would see this:

[IMAGE]
 
But Akif saw this:

[IMAGE]

All this got me wondering: how much fakeness is baked into being polite?

Politeness is theater. It's a performance that keeps social interactions predictable and respectful, especially between people who don't know each other that well. It's not always truthful, but just like we suspend our disbelief to enjoy a good story, we suspend our disbelief during interactions with others to make them go smoothly.

Yuval Harari's book Sapiens [2] suggests this suspension of disbelief is our species' big innovation. Unlike Neanderthals, we're able to work with strangers by believing in common fictions. Things like governments and money don't really exist, but by pretending they do, we can trust pharmacists to give us drugs that work, restaurants not to poison us, et cetera.

Politeness works similarly: it's another fiction acting as a social lubricant. So while there is something untrue baked into being polite, it's performance -- not fakeness.

Sometimes the politeness performance falls apart. When people with different backgrounds or personalities interact, it's like they're performing with different scripts.

ACT ONE

Scene I

<i>(On a busy street in Brussels, early in the morning. A young man approaches a black Audi.)</i>
Akif -- Danny?
Danny -- Yeah, that's me.
<i>(The young man enters the car.</i>

Scene II

<i>(The Audi races through traffic toward a bus station.)</I>
Danny -- Ugh, I already bought the ticket. I should have just waited until I got to the bus station. I just wasted 20 euros.
Akif -- I'm so sorry to hear that! Maybe if you're lucky the bus won't have left yet [strikethrough]. It's not like it's a flight or anything -- there's no need to exaggerate [red].

Actually, it's usually less that people are performing with different scripts and more that one of them doesn't know they're in a play. 

For example, saying hello when you walk into a shop or restaurant is super important in France (and a lot of other countries). Often Americans will go abroad, not acknowledge store clerks, and then complain about people being rude when they get bad service. 

When reaching across cultures, people just don't know their lines. They become rude (or honest?). So it's good to be generous and to remember that politeness is made up when someone from a different culture offends you.

[IMAGE]

 
