A thousand doors

Problem:

A thousand people line up in front of a thousand closed doors.

[fig. 0 a thousand people]
[fig. 1 a thousand doors]

Let "flipping" a door be the act of opening the door if it's closed or closing the door if it's open*.

The first person flips every door. 

[fig. 2 after the first person flips every door]

Next, the second person flips every second door.

[fig. 3 after the second person flips every second door]

Then the third person flips every third door.

[fig. 3 after the third person flips every third door]

This keeps going: the fourth person flips every fourth door, the fifth person flips every fifth door, and so on for all one thousand people. How many doors end up open? Why?

* I realized it would make more sense to use light switches after I had already drawn the pictures.

** Many thanks to my friend Maria for posing this problem on a road trip and to my colleague Drew for finding the solution before me.

Solution:

It turns out only 31 doors end up open: doors 1, 4, 9, 16, 25, and all the other perfect squares. Why is it only the perfect square doors that end up open? 

In a nutshell, 

(door ends up open -> door is flipped an odd number of times -> door number has an odd number of unique factors -> door number is a perfect square)


To see this a little more clearly, consider which people flip Door #15.

[fig. The first, third, fifth, and fifteenth people flip Door #15, leaving it closed.]

Door #15 gets flipped four times because 15 has four unique factors (1, 3, 5, and 15). In general, the number of times a door is flipped is the number of unique factors for that door's number.

Now consider Door #16. 

[fig. The first, second, fourth, eighth, and sixteenth people flip door #16, leaving it open.]

Door #16 gets flipped five times because 16 has five unique factors (1, 2, 4, 8, and 16). What's important here is that Door #16 gets flipped an odd number of times -- this is why it ends up open. 16 has an odd number of unique factors because it's a perfect square. 

So whether a door ends up open or closed comes down to whether it has an even or odd number of unique factors. Perfect squares like 16 are the only numbers with an odd number of factors (since their square roots lack accompanying factors).


Here's all that more formally:

Proposition 1. The nth person in line flips door m if and only if n is a factor of m.

Proof: 
Let n\in\N be a factor of m\in\N. Then nk=m for some k\in\N. Since person n flips every nth door, the kth door person n flips is door m.

For the converse, suppose n is not a factor of m and person n flips door m. Since person n only flips every nth door, there exists some k such that nk=m. This contradicts n not being a factor m.

Proposition 2. If a closed door is flipped an even number of times then it ends up closed. Also, if a door is flipped an odd number of times then it ends up open. 

Proof: Just think about it idk

Proposition 3. If a number has an odd number of unique factors, it's a perfect square.

We show the contrapositive. Let n be a positive integer that is not a perfect square and let \(S=s_1, s_2, \ldots, s_k\) be the set of n's unique factors. Suppose for contradiction k is odd. Then there exists no partition of S into two subsets of the same cardinality. So n must have an integer square root, contradicting its construction as not a perfect square.  

By proposition 1, the the number of times a door m is flipped is the same as the number of unique factors m has. Then by proposition 2, door m ends up open if and only m has an odd number of unique factors. Finally by proposition 3, door m ends up open if and only if m is a perfect square.

\qed